<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>John Lloyd on John Lloyd</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in John Lloyd on John Lloyd</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>Fox Sparrows move south</title>
      <link>/2019/10/22/fox-sparrows-move-south/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/10/22/fox-sparrows-move-south/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Late each fall, and then again early in spring, Fox Sparrows visit my backyard. Large and brightly colored, at least by sparrow standards, they are a harbinger of the changing seasons and a delight to watch during their brief stay. Sometimes they even sing during their brief spring stop-over, a beautiful set of downward, slurred whistles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most field guides and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Fox_Sparrow/maps-range&#34;&gt;general references&lt;/a&gt; depict Fox Sparrows as a bird that nests only in the boreal forest of Canada and Alaska and the high mountains of western North America. The eastern subspecies of Fox Sparrow—the Red Fox Sparrow (Passerella iliaca iliaca)—has traditionally been considered a passage migrant through New England, stopping off briefly in late fall and early spring as it travels to and from its breeding grounds in eastern Canada. However, several summers ago, while working in western Maine, I encountered several singing males in mid-June. As this seemed quite late for birds supposedly migrating through the region, I was intrigued. When I returned to camp that evening, I pulled off the shelf a copy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/26706#page/5/mode/1up&#34;&gt;Ralph Palmer’s Maine Birds&lt;/a&gt;, now almost 80 years old but still the definitive reference on the birdlife of Maine. As expected, Palmer describes Fox Sparrow as a “transient,” a passage migrant that moves through the state early in spring and again late in the fall but most certainly not a breeding species. So what were these birds that I’d found singing in the middle of June doing? Why was a species that supposedly only migrates through the region present during the breeding season and apparently defending territories?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These questions led to a two-year long effort to piece together its current breeding range, which &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/26706#page/5/mode/1up&#34;&gt;I’ve written about in a paper submitted for publication at the scientific journal PeerJ&lt;/a&gt;. The story goes something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beginning in the early 1980s, birders in southern Quebec—well south of the known range of the species—began noticing Fox Sparrows during the summer. A few years later, scientists working on a study of how efforts to control spruce-budworm outbreaks in Maine affected bird populations found a Fox Sparrow that they suspected was nesting. In 1983, a Fox Sparrow nest was finally discovered in far northwestern Maine, a stone’s throw from the Canadian border.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, the floodgates seem to have opened. Fox Sparrows were reported nearly every summer in increasingly far-flung locales, first in the mountains of western Maine, then near Mount Katahdin, and finally, by the mid-1990’s in northern New Hampshire. In 1996, a birder discovered the first Fox Sparrow nest in New Hampshire, near the northern town of Pittsburg. From there, they appear to have moved south, and are now a regular summertime resident throughout the White Mountains. A few have even showed up on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/26706#page/5/mode/1up&#34;&gt;Mountain Birdwatch&lt;/a&gt; surveys conducted in the Green Mountains of Vermont and at least one individual has been seen and heard singing on Whiteface Mountain in the Adirondacks of New York. Based on an analysis of checklists submitted to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ebird.org/map/foxspa?neg=true&amp;amp;env.minX=&amp;amp;env.minY=&amp;amp;env.maxX=&amp;amp;env.maxY=&amp;amp;zh=false&amp;amp;gp=false&amp;amp;ev=Z&amp;amp;mr=6-7&amp;amp;bmo=6&amp;amp;emo=7&amp;amp;yr=all&amp;amp;byr=1900&amp;amp;eyr=2018&#34;&gt;eBird&lt;/a&gt;, it seems that Fox Sparrows are showing up wherever there are young, dense forests of spruce and fir, whether it be the stunted krummholz forest of our mountaintops or the old clearcuts of commercial forestlands scattered throughout northern New Hampshire and western Maine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A species never known to nest in New England prior to the 1980s, Fox Sparrows have expanded their breeding range south by about 400 km in a span of less than 30 years, and seem to be on track to continue this remarkable journey. If past trends are any indicator of the future, they will likely become at least occasional nesters in suitable habitat in Vermont and New York (and indeed, may already be). Although I haven’t conducted an exhaustive search of the ornithological literature, I can think of few other bird species that have shifted their range so dramatically in such a short period of time, and none that have done so by moving north to south!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/fospMap.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The breeding range of Fox Sparrow (Passerella iliaca iliaca) has expanded southward out of Canada’s boreal forest by several hundred miles since the early 1980s. Colored dots on the map show the location and year of eBird checklists that contain an observation of Fox Sparrow.&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The breeding range of Fox Sparrow (&lt;em&gt;Passerella iliaca iliaca&lt;/em&gt;) has expanded southward out of Canada’s boreal forest by several hundred miles since the early 1980s. Colored dots on the map show the location and year of eBird checklists that contain an observation of Fox Sparrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What explains this phenomenon? Right now, the answer is anyone’s guess. One possibility, though, is that we’ve inadvertently created a lot of suitable habitat for Fox Sparrows through our logging activities. The Fox Sparrow vanguard arrived in Maine at about the same time that large areas of the state’s forests were being clearcut in response to the great spruce-budworm epidemic of the time. Dog-hair stands of spruce and fir sprung up in many of them. As a bird that loves thick stands of young evergreens, this may have offered a wealth of new nesting habitat that allowed new populations to become established and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve grown used to stories of climate change causing rapid shifts in the distribution of plants and animals across the globe, with southern species marching northward as the climate warms. Very rarely, though, do we see the opposite: a boreal species charging southward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much remains to be learned about our new breeding resident: what is driving the southward expansion, what implications exist for the species that make up the biological communities colonized by Fox Sparrows, and where Fox Sparrows will finally stop. In the meantime, though, keep an eye out as you explore the wilds of the northeast and don’t be surprised to see one of these boisterous northerners next summer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The recent expansion of Fox Sparrow (Passerella iliaca iliaca)  breeding range into the northeastern United States</title>
      <link>/publication/fosprangeexpansion/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/fosprangeexpansion/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Page</title>
      <link>/tutorial/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tutorial/example/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In this tutorial, I&amp;rsquo;ll share my top 10 tips for getting started with Academic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tip-1&#34;&gt;Tip 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tip-2&#34;&gt;Tip 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Policy</title>
      <link>/privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/privacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Co-creating a research agenda for biodiversity conservation</title>
      <link>/project/biodiversityroundtable/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/biodiversityroundtable/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In June 2016, we assembled a group of scientists, practitioners, and policy-makers who are involved professionally with biodiversity conservation and charged them with the task of co-creating a research agenda for biodiversity conservation in Vermont. Participants were asked to answer two questions in particular:
1) what are the key threats to biodiversity in Vermont, and
2) what knowledge do we need to address these threats?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By bringing together this diverse group of stakeholders and asking them to discuss these questions together, we sought to narrow the divides among science, policy, and action that have at times hindered development and implementation of effective biodiversity-conservation strategies. As Vermont enters an era of potentially rapid change in land use and land cover, brought about by large-scale processes including climate change and demographic and economic shifts that favor developed lands over wild or working lands, the need for unified conservation strategies that draw on the strengths of all stakeholders will become increasingly critical. Addressing this need requires dismantling the silos that separate scientists, conservation practitioners, and decision-makers. This dialogue event was a preliminary effort at doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full report is available at Figshare:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://figshare.com/articles/Co-creating_an_action-oriented_agenda_for_biodiversity_research_in_Vermont/5693221&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://figshare.com/articles/Co-creating_an_action-oriented_agenda_for_biodiversity_research_in_Vermont/5693221&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Natural history of the spruce-fir forests of the northeastern United States</title>
      <link>/project/sprucefirnaturalhistory/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/sprucefirnaturalhistory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Between the great deciduous forests of the eastern United States and the broad sweep of Canada&amp;rsquo;s evergreens lies a zone of ecological tension. Think of it as the dry land version of the intertidal zone: washed over by temperate waves of life from the south but deeply influenced by the boreal forests to its north. Neither life zone dominates, but instead both contribute elements, and the result is unique. Perhaps due to the chimeric nature of this life zone, or perhaps because it is overshadowed by its parents - two of the great biomes of the planet - we don&amp;rsquo;t have a good name for it. Instead, we call it the &amp;ldquo;spruce-fir forest&amp;rdquo;, with an occasional modifier to indicate whether it happens to be growing on a mountain top or a valley bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although boreal at first glance, the inland spruce-fir forest of the northeastern United States is in fact very much its own.  Wet and cloudy, it rarely burns, a marked contrast with the true boreal forests to the north, whose character is heavily influenced by fire. The spruces that give these forests half of their name are red spruce (&lt;em&gt;Picea rubens&lt;/em&gt;), not the white (&lt;em&gt;Picea glauca&lt;/em&gt;) or black spruce (&lt;em&gt;Picea mariana&lt;/em&gt;) of the boreal forest. Although it provides the southern-most home for icons of the boreal forest of Canada and Alaska like the Canada lynx (&lt;em&gt;Lynx lynx&lt;/em&gt;) and Canada jay (&lt;em&gt;Perisoreus canadensis&lt;/em&gt;), it is also inhabited by their southern relatives, bobcat (&lt;em&gt;Lynx rufus&lt;/em&gt;) and blue jay (&lt;em&gt;Cyanocitta cristata&lt;/em&gt;). And unlike the boreal forest, which wreathes the entire Northern Hemisphere, or the hardwood forests which stretched from the edge of the Great Plains to the Atlantic Ocean, the spruce-fir forest exists nowhere as a great stretch of unbroken forest. Instead, it occupies mountaintops from the Adirondack Mountains of New York to Maine&amp;rsquo;s Mount Katahdin and the cold, poorly drained valley bottoms in between. It is at its most extensive in the high, rolling hill country of western Maine and northern New Hampshire, encouraged by the favorable climate, poor soils, and intensive logging practices that characterize the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite its importance to people - from the Abenaki who ranged across this region to the rural communities that have formed within what is one of the most extensive blocks of commercial forestland in eastern North America- and as a redoubt for wild nature, the natural history of thus forests and its wild inhabitants remains poorly known. This represents an opportunity for advancing the science of ecology but at the same time poses a great challenge to our ability to use it wisely and sustainably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this project, I explore the natural history of the inland spruce-fir forests of the northeastern United States, shed light on the lives of its animals and plants, and seek to find solutions for its sustainable use by present-day human communities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Positive interactions under nurse-plants: spatial scale, stress gradients and benefactor size</title>
      <link>/publication/positiveinteractions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2001 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/positiveinteractions/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
