<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>John Lloyd on John Lloyd</title>
    <link>/</link>
    <description>Recent content in John Lloyd on John Lloyd</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sun, 15 Oct 2017 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>101 Natural History Books to Read Before You Die, No. 8</title>
      <link>/2020/05/27/almanac-for-mods/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/05/27/almanac-for-mods/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;This post originally appeared in the &lt;a href=&#34;https://naturalhistoryinstitute.org/journal-index/&#34;&gt;Journal of Natural History Education &amp;amp; Experience&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Natural-history writing comes in many flavors. Sometimes it takes the form of a catalog of observations of plants and animals, other times it presents accounts of exploration and adventure in the wild, and sometimes it is as much about the people as the landscape that shapes them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Nonetheless, perhaps because its subjects and themes appear so constant, it has to me a timeless feel. For better or worse, the style of the narrative tends towards the uniform, even as the subjects and themes differ widely.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What sets apart Donald Culross Peattie’s An Almanac for Moderns, first published in 1935, and what makes it such a unique contribution to this canon, is its blend of modern and classical styles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The tone is modernist, reflecting Peattie’s deep literary background. Even though he was a Harvard-trained scientist, for some years a botanist by trade, he was also a novelist, a columnist for several newspapers, and a poet. He was as connected to the world of letters – his mother a literary critic, father a journalist, and wife, Louise Redfield, an author – as he was to the world of science.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He did not wander into the wilderness for exploration or adventure, like young Aldo Leopold or Adolph Murie, but did much of his earlier writing from the prairie of Illinois (now a Chicago suburb) where he lived, worked, and raised his family. But instead of leading to the mundane, these ties to family, to work, and to a society on the verge of yet another global war lend his writing a feel at the same time more cosmopolitan than most natural history and more closely attuned to the common realities of life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In An Almanac for Moderns, Peattie writes with great detail about the lives of everything from slime molds to birds, often using the specifics of his observations as a springboard for discussing larger concepts in ecology and evolution. For example, in early October, he writes of his walks in the wet, autumn woods and of the sudden emergence of fungi of all sorts. This leads to a cataloging of the forms that he finds and finally to a discussion of the roles of decomposers and parasites. Ants, bees, and plants feature prominently in many of Peattie’s musing on natural history, presumably reflecting his background as a botanist and as a student of William Morton Wheeler, the great Harvard myrmecologist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;An Almanac for Moderns ranges widely, and extends into themes well beyond natural history. Peattie’s detours from the natural world showcase his novelist’s skill at self-expression and make for engrossing reading, for example where he tells in several beautiful passages of his young child’s battle with scarlet fever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To my eye, these are some of the best writings in the book, even if the natural world is more a symbol of restless fear than a subject of observation: “The singing of the cicadas began at dawn today and continued until sundown. It seemed to frighten the little boy so sick, so terrifyingly sick in bed; he talked of them through his fever in a confused way, and to the two of us, beside the bed, the cry of ‘Pharaoh’ rang out with a wail of fatality.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And the next day, June eleventh:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“The cicadas have ceased their singing with sundown, though tonight they woke up, once, like a renewal of my terrors, and wailed that their power was not yet broken. But even in the night silence the terrible sound of ten thousand knives shearing across ten thousand grindstones still rings in my head. I feel as though I would hear it forever, and forever remember when I stood by the window, waiting to hear what the thermometer would tell, certain that all joy is an elf gift and hope a treachery.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peattie’s interest in classical elements is most apparent in the organization of the essays. An Almanac for Moderns is arranged as series of short essays, one for each day of the year, split into sections corresponding to the astrological calendar. The daily writings tend to follow the changing seasons, but the phenology is interwoven with diversions into the lives of notable scientists and, perhaps on days when he found little outside to interest him, frank discourses on philosophy and the place of humankind in the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scientists celebrated by Peattie range from the obvious – Burroughs, Muir, Audubon – to the obscure. The lesser-known are more interesting in many ways, and Peattie’s descriptions of their lives have encouraged me to read more broadly. Thanks to Peattie, we meet characters like Sir John Lubbock, who, in addition to being a baron, a banker, and a member of Parliament, also turns out to have made significant contributions to archaeology and the study of Hymenoptera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peattie’s celebrations of the lives of scientists also include real drama. It is hard, for example, not to feel pity for Constantine Samuel Rafinesque, an erratically – and prolifically – creative polymath. He coined over 6,000 specific epithets in the North American flora (many of which have been subsequently ignored), investigated the systematics of fish and molluscs of the Ohio River, and wrote two volumes on the medical uses of plants of the United States. During his lifetime, his peers pilloried him in correspondence as an unprincipled, and perhaps unhinged, charlatan interested only in self-promotion, and he was publically played the fool by a bullying Audubon, who fed him lies and laughed as Rafinesque repeated them as truth. Rafinesque died alone and penniless, his body discovered by a landlord who then attempted to sell the corpse to recoup a debt. As if that were not indignity enough for one lifetime, he was denounced posthumously by Asa Gray as a delusional liar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Peattie finds humor in his subjects, too. He recounts the tale of Alexander Wilson, “the first great ornithologist of America,” who was set upon by a captive Ivory-billed Woodpecker, ostensibly the subject of a painting. The erstwhile captive “violently attacked Wilson about the face,” forcing a hasty retreat from the North Carolina hotel room where the young Wilson was working. Wilson returned later to find the room in shambles, and the bird nearly done with a hole excavated through the entirety of one wall.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The digressions into philosophy reflect a worldview that seems shaped equally by both a love of the natural world and a fear – no doubt born of the lingering disillusionment with humanity following the First World War – of what humans are capable of doing unto themselves and the world around them. Peattie argues throughout the book for a philosophy based on the supremacy of biological laws; “[t]here is no philosophy with a shadow of realism about it, save a philosophy based upon Nature.” We cannot understand ourselves, says Peattie, without recognizing our place in the natural world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And because of his conviction that we are part and parcel of the natural world, Peattie is vehement in his condemnation of our trespasses against it. Indeed, he is at his most lyrical as he concludes a cataloging of the ways in which we waste the bounty that surrounds us: “And in the end [man] may present the spectacle of some Brobdingnagian spoiled baby, gulping down his cake and howling for it too.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some days Peattie has little to say, which I find humanizing; I would find less common ground with someone capable of uninterrupted inspiration. An Almanac for Moderns is not the kind of prose that keeps one reading into the small hours, but it always pulls me in for longer than I plan. Despite several efforts to do so, I have never been able to read An Almanac for Moderns as some have suggested it should be: day-by-day, following the course of the year. I pick it up, and put it down, but I am always drawn to read just one more essay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a book that will provide much new insight into the natural history of the Midwestern United States, and indeed many of Peattie’s musings on evolution and life history are dated or simply wrong: monarch butterflies (Danaus plexippus) do migrate, Ivory-billed Woodpeckers (Campephilus principalis) did not inhabit the forests of Brazil, and fireflies (Coleoptera:Lampyridae) do not glow because of internal, luminous bacteria. Modern readers will find Peattie’s views on race, and to a lesser extent gender, regressive, but these digressions are mercifully brief and hardly malicious.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite these failings, it is a lyrical and wide-ranging and thoughtfully crafted book about the natural world and our place in it, and for me it has served as a reminder of the romance of natural history and the value of being aware of the lives lived all around us. Natural history is not a practice only for the mountaintop or remote rainforest; we may, as Peattie believed, learn as much observing the ants amidst the cracks of the sidewalk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like most of us, he yearned for the sublime at times – “I would go now, if I could, to the mountains…some gentle hills, mere unevenness in the land, will not help me” – but never scorned or overlooked the commonplace. It is an inspiring and reassuring book, especially for those of us lacking the Skutchian patience needed to stare unblinking at a bird’s nest for days on end, or whose careers and lives will not be spent describing new species or traveling unmapped wilderness. No matter where we are, or what we do, we can remember always that “Life, brother, is not all mankind…[w]ait with me a little; only listen to the soft, tremendous footfalls of a destiny that is greater than ours; hear a while the hum of summer, for it is not only the scraping of the small chitinous instruments of insects; it is the singing of the world’s blood as it runs in your own veins and sounds in your own ears.”&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The Migratory Bird Treaty Act and bird conservation</title>
      <link>/2020/03/06/losing-protections-for-birds/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 06 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2020/03/06/losing-protections-for-birds/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Last December, a team led by scientist Tatsuya Amano from the University of Oxford’s Conservation Science Group published an &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/nature25139&#34;&gt;important paper on waterbird conservation&lt;/a&gt;. Using data collected across the globe, they examined population changes over the past 3 decades in 461 species of waterbird, including everything from ducks to shorebirds to flamingos. During this time, waterbirds in some parts of the world thrived, but in other places they experienced steep declines. When the scientists looked for an explanation for this pattern, they were able to isolate two key predictors of whether waterbird populations shrunk or grew.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Predictably, the loss of surface water explained some of the decline in waterbird numbers. Central Asia, for example, has lost vast amounts of its surface water due to drought, diversion and damming of rivers, and unregulated water withdrawals for human use; waterbird populations in this part of the world declined steeply. This makes sense: without surface water, these species have no place to live.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surprisingly, more important even than the loss of surface water was the role of effective governance. Waterbirds declined significantly in countries with weak or ineffective governments, but their numbers grew in countries that were politically stable and well-governed. The &lt;a href=&#34;http://info.worldbank.org/governance/wgi/index.aspx#reports&#34;&gt;overall effectiveness of a country’s government&lt;/a&gt;, quantified annually by the World Bank, includes a variety of factors like regulatory quality, rule of law, control of corruption, and accountability, but the most likely link between waterbird population health and governance is through the environmental aspects of governmental regulation. When countries have well-enforced environmental rules and high levels of investment in conservation, waterbirds – and presumably other wildlife – thrive. For example, Iran, with &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.cambridge.org/core/journals/bird-conservation-international/article/an-assessment-of-threats-to-anatidae-in-iran/47CDE29CA4E1533D2EF2F560186912B9&#34;&gt;weak regulation of hunting and limited protections for wetlands&lt;/a&gt;, saw substantial declines in waterbirds. During the same time period, waterbirds thrived throughout the countries of the European Union, where protections for birds and their habitats are stringent.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Coincidentally, two days after this study of waterbird populations was published, the US Department of Interior announced that it would no longer strictly enforce the Migratory Bird Treaty Act, one of our oldest and most important environmental laws, and one of the few that specifically protects birds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.law.cornell.edu/uscode/text/16/chapter-7/subchapter-II&#34;&gt;Migratory Bird Treaty Act&lt;/a&gt; was originally enacted in 1918 to implement a convention on bird conservation between the US and Great Britain, acting as the sovereign of Canada. The Act was later amended to implement conventions with three other nations that share bird populations with the US: Mexico, Russia, and Japan. Enacted at a time when bird populations faced devastating threats from commercial hunting, the intent of the law was clear: to promote bird conservation by prohibiting the unregulated killing of wild birds. Although clearly motivated by the wanton slaughter of birds taking place at the time, the language of the Act itself is general. Simply put, except as otherwise expressly allowed, it is illegal, “at any time, by any means or in any manner”, to kill any bird that is protected under the Act or to take its nest or eggs.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Trump administration prefers a different interpretation. According to its &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.endangeredspecieslawandpolicy.com/files/2017/12/m-37050.pdf&#34;&gt;memorandum&lt;/a&gt;, the Department of Interior now views only those actions “that have as their purpose the taking or killing of migratory birds, their nests or their eggs” as violations of the Act. In other words, only actions intended to directly kill birds count as violations of the Act. This upends the interpretation that has been held by every prior administration in recent history – Republican or Democrat – from Richard Nixon to Barack Obama, which was quite simple: the Act prohibits the unregulated killing of birds, whether the intent was to kill them or not.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is not a picayune distinction. Market hunters and milliners are no longer the preeminent threats to bird populations in North America. Outside of the closely regulated and sustainable hunting of game birds, most human-caused bird deaths in the US are inadvertent. Each year we &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.annualreviews.org/doi/full/10.1146/annurev-ecolsys-112414-054133&#34;&gt;unintentionally kill hundreds of thousands of birds&lt;/a&gt; when when they are poisoned by pesticides or in tailing ponds at mines or oil wells, when they collide with wind turbines or communication towers, or when they are caught accidentally in gill nets. The Migratory Bird Treaty Act has been the only tool to address these important but otherwise unregulated sources of mortality, and now even that modest bastion of regulation looks to have fallen by the wayside.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/Forsters-tern.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;A Forster’s Tern accidentally entangled in fishing net. From the article “Hope for Migratory Sea Birds” by Cynthia Henderson Vega, which appeared in the Winter 2000 issue of [Coastwatch](https://archive.org/stream/coastwatch00uncs_13/#page/25/mode/1up)&#34; /&gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    A Forster’s Tern accidentally entangled in fishing net. From the article “Hope for Migratory Sea Birds” by Cynthia Henderson Vega, which appeared in the Winter 2000 issue of &lt;a href=&#34;https://archive.org/stream/coastwatch00uncs_13/#page/25/mode/1up&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Coastwatch&lt;/a&gt;
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Department of Interior relied in part on judicial uncertainty to justify its reinterpretation of the Act as a prohibition only on illegal hunting and unregulated oology. And indeed, courts have long split on how to interpret the meaning of the statutory language. Some have held that the Act applies to any activity that results in the killing of birds, whereas others have held that the Act only applies when birds were intentionally killed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yet the Act has been a successful tool for bird conservation despite this uncertainty. In a &lt;a href=&#34;https://defenders.org/publications/mbta-zinke.pdf&#34;&gt;remarkable letter&lt;/a&gt;, 17 former high-level Department of Interior officials, including political appointees from the Obama, Clinton, and George W. Bush administrations, wrote Secretary of the Interior Ryan Zinke encouraging him to reconsider this policy. As they put it, the Act “can and has been successfully used to reduce gross negligence by companies that simply do not recognize the value of birds to society or the practical means to minimize harm. Your new interpretation needlessly undermines a history of great progress, undermines the effectiveness of the migratory bird treaties, and diminishes U.S. leadership.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Under previous administrations, the Fish and Wildlife Service, empowered by a commitment to conservation at the highest levels of government, used the Act to signal the seriousness with which they viewed any activity that led to death of birds. Industries whose activities threatened bird populations – oil and gas, fishing, coal, wind and solar power, and electric-transmission utilities, to name a few – understood the rules and, as a result, acted proactively to take measures to minimize the risk that they would, in the course of carrying out otherwise-legal business activities, kill birds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;With the Trump administration signaling its lack of interest in holding industries accountable for causing unnecessary bird deaths, little incentive exists for maintaining the common-sense conservation measures that previous interpretations of the Act required. Oil producers working to keep migratory birds away from toxic tailing ponds or wind-power companies that shut turbines down during peak bird-migration times may see no reason to continue these activities. Commercial fishing fleets need no longer worry about solving the problem of seabirds drowning in nets or on baited lines. One of my first jobs out of school involved helping engineering firms to comply with the Migratory Bird Treaty Act during the construction of bridges and roads, which generally involved things as simple as waiting to tear down an old bridge until Cliff Swallow colonies had fledged their young. Now, even minor acts of conservation like this will be harder to come by.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;

&lt;img src=&#34;/img/cliff-swallows.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Cliff Swallows nesting beneath a bridge in North Carolina. Photo by [Ken Thomas](http://kenthomas.us).&#34; /&gt;



&lt;figcaption data-pre=&#34;Figure &#34; data-post=&#34;:&#34; &gt;
  &lt;p&gt;
    Cliff Swallows nesting beneath a bridge in North Carolina. Photo by &lt;a href=&#34;http://kenthomas.us&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;Ken Thomas&lt;/a&gt;.
    
    
    
  &lt;/p&gt; 
&lt;/figcaption&gt;

&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Given the scope and breadth of the Act, the significance of the recent change in interpretation by the Trump administration is not easily overstated. The Act currently affords protection for more than 1,000 bird species, including every species native to the US. Indeed, it is the only legal protection for most of them; unless a bird species is otherwise specifically protected by law – for example by the Endangered Species Act or the &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.fws.gov/midwest/midwestbird/eaglepermits/bagepa.html&#34;&gt;Bald and Golden Eagle Protection Act&lt;/a&gt; – then regulations promulgated under the Migratory Bird Treaty Act represent their only formal line of defense. This would include almost any bird that you’ve seen in Vermont in the past year: Hermit Thrush or Scarlet Tanager, Tree Swallow or Chimney Swift; none are specifically protected by any Federal law save for the Migratory Bird Treaty Act.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we know from the Tatsuya Amano’s work on waterbirds, and from our country’s own history of successes and failures in bird conservation, weak or inconsistently enforced laws and stingy investments in conservation will eventually lead to the demise of wildlife populations. Unfortunately, we appear well on our way to meeting both of these conditions. Federal and state investment in conservation in the US has declined sharply over the past decade (for example, see here or here) and, with the decision to weaken the Migratory Bird Treaty Act, and similar efforts targeting the Endangered Species Act, we are poised to enter an era of in which environmentally damaging activities will no longer face strict regulation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The US Congress enacted the Migratory Bird Treaty Act in 1918 as a response to our collective failure to regulate our own worst behaviors, and in doing so created the conditions that allowed for one of the great conservation success stories of all time. Now, in the form of a 41-page memorandum, we face a failure of governance that may undo many of the gains we have realized in bird conservation. What’s more, we risk these gains for no good reason: the change in policy is a solution in search of a problem. For decades, administrations of all political stripes have found ways to balance the needs of people and of birds within the broad outlines of the Migratory Bird Treaty Act. Abandoning the principles of conservation enshrined in the Act will benefit few, if any, people, but will surely come at a cost to the birds that we all cherish.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why are Hairy Woodpeckers and Downy Woodpeckers so hard to tell apart?</title>
      <link>/2019/10/24/hairy-downy-woodpeckers-lookalikes/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/10/24/hairy-downy-woodpeckers-lookalikes/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;As winter descends and the days become cold and short, most of my birdwatching becomes rather narrowly focused on the feeders outside my front door. A walk through my woods in winter, although lovely in its own right, tends to yield fairly few birds. If I’m lucky, I might come across a noisy flock of Golden-crowned Kinglets, Black-capped Chickadees, and Brown Creepers. Just as easily, though, I can spend an hour wandering through the snow in absolute silence; the trees seem empty of birdlife.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The feeders, though, are comparatively busy: in some winters, I’m visited by hundreds of Common Redpolls, although this year so far has been the year of the Dark-eyed Junco. Dozens of them have been daily at my feeders since before the snow fell, and with the storm of last week they’ve taken to perching on the feeders, a behavior I don’t recall seeing so commonly before.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then there are the regulars, always present as soon as I fill the feeders in early winter. Chickadees, Tufted Titmice, American Goldfinches, hordes of Blue Jays, a hardy trio of Northern Cardinals, and a rotating cast of Downy Woodpeckers and Hairy Woodpeckers. The last two species pose a real challenge for many birdwatchers. Similar in almost every feature of their plumage, they are most readily distinguishable by their size. Hairy Woodpeckers are about 50% again as big as Downy Woodpeckers, and carry a relatively longer bill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite their close resemblance of one another, &lt;a href=&#34;http://digitalcommons.wayne.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1005&amp;amp;context=biosci_frp&#34;&gt;various studies&lt;/a&gt; have revealed that these two species are in fact not close relatives of one another. Downy Woodpeckers are probably more closely related to two species of western North America, &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.audubon.org/field-guide/bird/nuttalls-woodpecker&#34;&gt;Nuttall’s Woodpecker&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.audubon.org/field-guide/bird/ladder-backed-woodpecker&#34;&gt;Ladder-backed Woodpecker&lt;/a&gt;. Hairy Woodpeckers, by contrast, are a sister to the &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.audubon.org/field-guide/bird/arizona-woodpecker&#34;&gt;Arizona Woodpecker&lt;/a&gt; and the Mexican endemic &lt;a href=&#34;https://neotropical.birds.cornell.edu/Species-Account/nb/species/strwoo/overview&#34;&gt;Strickland’s Woodpecker&lt;/a&gt;. Indeed, to find the closest common ancestor of Hairy and Downy woodpeckers, one must travel all the way back in time to the primordial Picoides woodpecker, the mother of all subsequent species in this genus (I should point out that woodpeckers are no exception to the rule that no taxonomy is ever certain; &lt;a href=&#34;https://s3.amazonaws.com/academia.edu.documents/42675903/A_new_classification_of_the_Pied_Woodpec20160214-25338-1svl4qr.pdf?AWSAccessKeyId=AKIAIWOWYYGZ2Y53UL3A&amp;amp;Expires=1513612157&amp;amp;Signature=9qcLfCIXn6xiLSoAYnl2u57vwAw%3D&amp;amp;response-content-disposition=inline%3B%20filename%3DA_new_classification_of_the_Pied_Woodpec.pdf&#34;&gt;one recent study&lt;/a&gt; argues that Hairy and Downy woodpeckers are neither in the same genus nor belong in Picoides. Nonetheless, the point remains: they aren’t the closest of relatives).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That these two species were not especially close relatives came as some surprise to ornithologists. Plumage similarities of the sort exhibited by Downy and Hairy woodpeckers tend to reflect a recent, shared evolutionary history; in the parlance of evolutionary biologists these shared characteristics are homologous, or features inherited from a common ancestor. Humans have forelimbs that are anatomically similar to salamanders, cats, whales, and every other vertebrate because we share a common ancestor, not because each group independently evolved the same set of bones. In other words, we assumed that these woodpeckers looked alike because they were alike.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the case of Downy and Hairy woodpeckers, however, the similarities are not homologous. Each is more closely related to a very different looking group of woodpeckers (cases in point: Hairy Woodpeckers are more closely related to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.audubon.org/field-guide/bird/white-headed-woodpecker&#34;&gt;White-headed Woodpeckers&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Smoky-brown_woodpecker&#34;&gt;Smoky-brown Woodpeckers&lt;/a&gt; than to Downy Woodpeckers), which rules out the possibility that they inherited their matching plumages from a common ancestor. Chances are that the common ancestor of both looked quite different from either. This means that the more likely explanation for being look-alikes is that the resemblance is evolved. For some reason, two different-looking species have come to appear quite the same.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Mimicry is widespread in nature, perhaps the most familiar example being &lt;a href=&#34;https://scholarblogs.emory.edu/evolutionshorts/2014/04/16/survival-of-the-fittest-monarch-and-viceroy-butterflies/&#34;&gt;Monarch and Viceroy butterflies&lt;/a&gt;. As adults, Monarchs are unpalatable to potential predators because they sequester toxic compounds gained from the milkweed they consume as caterpillars, and the Viceroy was thought to have evolved as a mimic to take advantage of this protection from predation. This has long been held as the iconic example of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Batesian_mimicry&#34;&gt;Batesian mimicry&lt;/a&gt;, in which a palatable or poorly defended species comes over evolutionary time to resemble a toxic or otherwise dangerous species. More recently, &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.nature.com/articles/350497a0&#34;&gt;some evidence&lt;/a&gt; suggests that the Viceroy is itself unpalatable, which means that the mimicry is instead &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/M%C3%BCllerian_mimicry&#34;&gt;Mullerian&lt;/a&gt;, wherein two equally dangerous species come to mimic one another’s warning signals, thus reinforcing, for example, the danger of eating any large, orange butterfly. Whereas Batesian mimicry is about tricking predators into thinking you are inedible, Mullerian mimicry is all about consistent messaging to potential predators.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It isn’t likely that the similarities between Hairy and Downy woodpeckers have anything to do with this kind of mimicry, however. As far as we know, both would make a perfectly good meal for a hungry Sharp-shinned Hawk. So why have these two species evolved to look nearly the same as one another? &lt;a href=&#34;http://digitalcommons.wayne.edu/cgi/viewcontent.cgi?article=1005&amp;amp;context=biosci_frp&#34;&gt;The first ornithologists to describe this apparent case of evolved similarity&lt;/a&gt; struggled to offer a plausible explanation. Recently, though, Yale University professor of ornithology Richard Prum has proposed an &lt;a href=&#34;https://prumlab.yale.edu/sites/default/files/prum_samuelson_mimicry_ms.pdf&#34;&gt;interesting and novel explanation&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;He argues that Downy Woodpeckers benefit by looking like the larger and more aggressive Hairy Woodpecker because it reduces the chance of an attack by a Hairy Woodpecker. Based on our understanding of avian vision, the size difference between the two species is difficult for a bird to perceive at a distance of more than a few meters. This means that a Hairy Woodpecker approaching a Downy Woodpecker may easily mistake it for another Hairy Woodpecker because the one distinguishing feature – size – is imperceptible at distance. A Hairy Woodpecker could always use its larger size to chase a Downy Woodpecker away from a prime feeding spot or potential nest cavity, but would have no such guarantee should it choose to battle another Hairy Woodpecker. As such, Downy Woodpeckers might occasionally avoid a fight – one they are sure to lose – simply by tricking their larger opponent into misjudging the odds of victory. If the two species compete for feeding and nesting opportunities, as they seem to do, then a win here and there due to this trickery might offer a real evolutionary advantage to mimicry. And mimicry doesn’t have to work every time; it just has to work often enough to give some small advantage to Downy Woodpeckers that more closely resemble Hairy Woodpeckers. Over time, with natural selection acting to reward mimics, Downy Woodpeckers might plausibly evolve to closely resemble their larger cousin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://academic.oup.com/zoolinnean/article/172/4/910/2433421&#34;&gt;Prum has identified nearly 100 other cases of avian mimicry&lt;/a&gt; that might have evolved in similar fashion. One of the more spectacular examples is the mimicry of the &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Eurasian_sparrowhawk&#34;&gt;Eurasian Sparrowhawk&lt;/a&gt; by several species of &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Common_cuckoo&#34;&gt;Old World cuckoo&lt;/a&gt;. Presumably, a cuckoo that looks like a hawk is less likely to be singled out for attack by another hawk. The cuckoos are such good mimics that they fool not only people (a fine example came during &lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Edgar_Chance&#34;&gt;Edgar Chance’s&lt;/a&gt; early studies of the common cuckoo in England: &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC2587796/#bib3&#34;&gt;one of his study birds was nearly shot and killed by a villager convinced that the bird was a hawk&lt;/a&gt;) but even other birds; tits – which are neither eaten nor harassed in any way by cuckoos – respond to cuckoos as though they were a predatory hawk.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although perhaps less dramatic, Lesser Yellowlegs and Greater Yellowlegs provide another example familiar to birdwatchers in the northeastern United States. These species are not close relatives of one another (Lesser Yellowlegs are closer genetically to &lt;a href=&#34;http://www.audubon.org/field-guide/bird/willet&#34;&gt;Willets&lt;/a&gt; than to Greater Yellowlegs), yet, as many of us have discovered with chagrin, they are nearly identical in appearance. Might this similarity of form ease the burden of competition for the smaller of the two species?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/gryeLeye.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;Greater Yellowlegs and Lesser Yellowlegs, side-by-side. Which is which? Photo by Dominic Sherony (CC BY-SA 2.0), via Wikimedia Commons.&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;Greater Yellowlegs and Lesser Yellowlegs, side-by-side. Which is which? Photo by Dominic Sherony (CC BY-SA 2.0), via Wikimedia Commons.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fox Sparrows move south</title>
      <link>/2019/10/22/fox-sparrows-move-south/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Oct 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/2019/10/22/fox-sparrows-move-south/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Late each fall, and then again early in spring, Fox Sparrows visit my backyard. Large and brightly colored, at least by sparrow standards, they are a harbinger of the changing seasons and a delight to watch during their brief stay. Sometimes they even sing during their brief spring stop-over, a beautiful set of downward, slurred whistles.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Most field guides and &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.allaboutbirds.org/guide/Fox_Sparrow/maps-range&#34;&gt;general references&lt;/a&gt; depict Fox Sparrows as a bird that nests only in the boreal forest of Canada and Alaska and the high mountains of western North America. The eastern subspecies of Fox Sparrow—the Red Fox Sparrow (Passerella iliaca iliaca)—has traditionally been considered a passage migrant through New England, stopping off briefly in late fall and early spring as it travels to and from its breeding grounds in eastern Canada. However, several summers ago, while working in western Maine, I encountered several singing males in mid-June. As this seemed quite late for birds supposedly migrating through the region, I was intrigued. When I returned to camp that evening, I pulled off the shelf a copy of &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/26706#page/5/mode/1up&#34;&gt;Ralph Palmer’s Maine Birds&lt;/a&gt;, now almost 80 years old but still the definitive reference on the birdlife of Maine. As expected, Palmer describes Fox Sparrow as a “transient,” a passage migrant that moves through the state early in spring and again late in the fall but most certainly not a breeding species. So what were these birds that I’d found singing in the middle of June doing? Why was a species that supposedly only migrates through the region present during the breeding season and apparently defending territories?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These questions led to a two-year long effort to piece together its current breeding range, which &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/26706#page/5/mode/1up&#34;&gt;I’ve written about in a paper submitted for publication at the scientific journal PeerJ&lt;/a&gt;. The story goes something like this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Beginning in the early 1980s, birders in southern Quebec—well south of the known range of the species—began noticing Fox Sparrows during the summer. A few years later, scientists working on a study of how efforts to control spruce-budworm outbreaks in Maine affected bird populations found a Fox Sparrow that they suspected was nesting. In 1983, a Fox Sparrow nest was finally discovered in far northwestern Maine, a stone’s throw from the Canadian border.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After that, the floodgates seem to have opened. Fox Sparrows were reported nearly every summer in increasingly far-flung locales, first in the mountains of western Maine, then near Mount Katahdin, and finally, by the mid-1990’s in northern New Hampshire. In 1996, a birder discovered the first Fox Sparrow nest in New Hampshire, near the northern town of Pittsburg. From there, they appear to have moved south, and are now a regular summertime resident throughout the White Mountains. A few have even showed up on &lt;a href=&#34;https://www.biodiversitylibrary.org/item/26706#page/5/mode/1up&#34;&gt;Mountain Birdwatch&lt;/a&gt; surveys conducted in the Green Mountains of Vermont and at least one individual has been seen and heard singing on Whiteface Mountain in the Adirondacks of New York. Based on an analysis of checklists submitted to &lt;a href=&#34;https://ebird.org/map/foxspa?neg=true&amp;amp;env.minX=&amp;amp;env.minY=&amp;amp;env.maxX=&amp;amp;env.maxY=&amp;amp;zh=false&amp;amp;gp=false&amp;amp;ev=Z&amp;amp;mr=6-7&amp;amp;bmo=6&amp;amp;emo=7&amp;amp;yr=all&amp;amp;byr=1900&amp;amp;eyr=2018&#34;&gt;eBird&lt;/a&gt;, it seems that Fox Sparrows are showing up wherever there are young, dense forests of spruce and fir, whether it be the stunted krummholz forest of our mountaintops or the old clearcuts of commercial forestlands scattered throughout northern New Hampshire and western Maine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A species never known to nest in New England prior to the 1980s, Fox Sparrows have expanded their breeding range south by about 400 km in a span of less than 30 years, and seem to be on track to continue this remarkable journey. If past trends are any indicator of the future, they will likely become at least occasional nesters in suitable habitat in Vermont and New York (and indeed, may already be). Although I haven’t conducted an exhaustive search of the ornithological literature, I can think of few other bird species that have shifted their range so dramatically in such a short period of time, and none that have done so by moving north to south!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class=&#34;figure&#34;&gt;
&lt;img src=&#34;/img/fospMap.jpg&#34; alt=&#34;The breeding range of Fox Sparrow (Passerella iliaca iliaca) has expanded southward out of Canada’s boreal forest by several hundred miles since the early 1980s. Colored dots on the map show the location and year of eBird checklists that contain an observation of Fox Sparrow.&#34; /&gt;
&lt;p class=&#34;caption&#34;&gt;The breeding range of Fox Sparrow (&lt;em&gt;Passerella iliaca iliaca&lt;/em&gt;) has expanded southward out of Canada’s boreal forest by several hundred miles since the early 1980s. Colored dots on the map show the location and year of eBird checklists that contain an observation of Fox Sparrow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What explains this phenomenon? Right now, the answer is anyone’s guess. One possibility, though, is that we’ve inadvertently created a lot of suitable habitat for Fox Sparrows through our logging activities. The Fox Sparrow vanguard arrived in Maine at about the same time that large areas of the state’s forests were being clearcut in response to the great spruce-budworm epidemic of the time. Dog-hair stands of spruce and fir sprung up in many of them. As a bird that loves thick stands of young evergreens, this may have offered a wealth of new nesting habitat that allowed new populations to become established and grow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’ve grown used to stories of climate change causing rapid shifts in the distribution of plants and animals across the globe, with southern species marching northward as the climate warms. Very rarely, though, do we see the opposite: a boreal species charging southward.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Much remains to be learned about our new breeding resident: what is driving the southward expansion, what implications exist for the species that make up the biological communities colonized by Fox Sparrows, and where Fox Sparrows will finally stop. In the meantime, though, keep an eye out as you explore the wilds of the northeast and don’t be surprised to see one of these boisterous northerners next summer.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The recent expansion of Fox Sparrow (Passerella iliaca iliaca)  breeding range into the northeastern United States</title>
      <link>/publication/fosprangeexpansion/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/fosprangeexpansion/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Example Page</title>
      <link>/tutorial/example/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 09 Sep 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/tutorial/example/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In this tutorial, I&amp;rsquo;ll share my top 10 tips for getting started with Academic:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tip-1&#34;&gt;Tip 1&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tip-2&#34;&gt;Tip 2&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Privacy Policy</title>
      <link>/privacy/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 28 Jun 2018 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/privacy/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Co-creating a research agenda for biodiversity conservation</title>
      <link>/project/biodiversityroundtable/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/biodiversityroundtable/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;In June 2016, we assembled a group of scientists, practitioners, and policy-makers who are involved professionally with biodiversity conservation and charged them with the task of co-creating a research agenda for biodiversity conservation in Vermont. Participants were asked to answer two questions in particular:
1) what are the key threats to biodiversity in Vermont, and
2) what knowledge do we need to address these threats?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;By bringing together this diverse group of stakeholders and asking them to discuss these questions together, we sought to narrow the divides among science, policy, and action that have at times hindered development and implementation of effective biodiversity-conservation strategies. As Vermont enters an era of potentially rapid change in land use and land cover, brought about by large-scale processes including climate change and demographic and economic shifts that favor developed lands over wild or working lands, the need for unified conservation strategies that draw on the strengths of all stakeholders will become increasingly critical. Addressing this need requires dismantling the silos that separate scientists, conservation practitioners, and decision-makers. This dialogue event was a preliminary effort at doing so.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The full report is available at Figshare:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://figshare.com/articles/Co-creating_an_action-oriented_agenda_for_biodiversity_research_in_Vermont/5693221&#34; target=&#34;_blank&#34;&gt;https://figshare.com/articles/Co-creating_an_action-oriented_agenda_for_biodiversity_research_in_Vermont/5693221&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Natural history of the spruce-fir forests of the northeastern United States</title>
      <link>/project/sprucefirnaturalhistory/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Apr 2016 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/sprucefirnaturalhistory/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Between the great deciduous forests of the eastern United States and the broad sweep of Canada&amp;rsquo;s evergreens lies a zone of ecological tension. Think of it as the dry land version of the intertidal zone: washed over by temperate waves of life from the south but deeply influenced by the boreal forests to its north. Neither life zone dominates, but instead both contribute elements, and the result is unique. Perhaps due to the chimeric nature of this life zone, or perhaps because it is overshadowed by its parents - two of the great biomes of the planet - we don&amp;rsquo;t have a good name for it. Instead, we call it the &amp;ldquo;spruce-fir forest&amp;rdquo;, with an occasional modifier to indicate whether it happens to be growing on a mountain top or a valley bottom.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Although boreal at first glance, the inland spruce-fir forest of the northeastern United States is in fact very much its own.  Wet and cloudy, it rarely burns, a marked contrast with the true boreal forests to the north, whose character is heavily influenced by fire. The spruces that give these forests half of their name are red spruce (&lt;em&gt;Picea rubens&lt;/em&gt;), not the white (&lt;em&gt;Picea glauca&lt;/em&gt;) or black spruce (&lt;em&gt;Picea mariana&lt;/em&gt;) of the boreal forest. Although it provides the southern-most home for icons of the boreal forest of Canada and Alaska like the Canada lynx (&lt;em&gt;Lynx lynx&lt;/em&gt;) and Canada jay (&lt;em&gt;Perisoreus canadensis&lt;/em&gt;), it is also inhabited by their southern relatives, bobcat (&lt;em&gt;Lynx rufus&lt;/em&gt;) and blue jay (&lt;em&gt;Cyanocitta cristata&lt;/em&gt;). And unlike the boreal forest, which wreathes the entire Northern Hemisphere, or the hardwood forests which stretched from the edge of the Great Plains to the Atlantic Ocean, the spruce-fir forest exists nowhere as a great stretch of unbroken forest. Instead, it occupies mountaintops from the Adirondack Mountains of New York to Maine&amp;rsquo;s Mount Katahdin and the cold, poorly drained valley bottoms in between. It is at its most extensive in the high, rolling hill country of western Maine and northern New Hampshire, encouraged by the favorable climate, poor soils, and intensive logging practices that characterize the area.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Despite its importance to people - from the Abenaki who ranged across this region to the rural communities that have formed within what is one of the most extensive blocks of commercial forestland in eastern North America- and as a redoubt for wild nature, the natural history of thus forests and its wild inhabitants remains poorly known. This represents an opportunity for advancing the science of ecology but at the same time poses a great challenge to our ability to use it wisely and sustainably.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In this project, I explore the natural history of the inland spruce-fir forests of the northeastern United States, shed light on the lives of its animals and plants, and seek to find solutions for its sustainable use by present-day human communities.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Positive interactions under nurse-plants: spatial scale, stress gradients and benefactor size</title>
      <link>/publication/positiveinteractions/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 May 2001 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/publication/positiveinteractions/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
